Okay, today's דף daf is קב Kuf-Bet 102 and we started with
a ברייתא braita at the bottom of קא עמוד ב Kuf-Aleph Amud
Bet which is worth rereading. So let's pick up from there. The
גמרא Gemara had just given an answer to try to figure out
where you've got these extra corner things that might be how they
could fit according to Rav Shimon's reading and said maybe we're talking
about little things there for infant. I think I explained yesterday also
that the גמרא Gemara was using that to solve the question here
of intersecting graves that would logically occur from having four of them,
four caves, but it seems like the גמרא Gemara was not saying
that. It was actually only using that to answer the infant one,
that this answer would still be an issue about having them at
different levels. So I just wanted to clarify that point. Anyway, let's
pick up with the משנה mishna at the bottom of קא עמוד
ב. Kuf-Aleph Amud Bet. תנן התם, Tenan Hatam, we taught over there,
the over there being in אהלות, Oholot, so I presume everybody recognizes
this משנה mishna from their learning of משניות אהלות. Mishnayot Oholot. תנן
התם Tenan Hatam we taught over there, המוצא מת מושכב כדרכו, Hamotzei
Meit Mushkav Kedarko, you find in a field a body that's buried
and it's lying it's been laid the way you would expect a
body to be laid down if it was being buried
as opposed to like if it had fallen in war or been
murdered, put in some strange way that does not indicate burial. This
one is being laid down to indicate burial. In that case, laid
down right way, let's say it was laid down upside down. That
might make a difference. נוטלו
ואת תפוסתו, Notlo Ve'et Tefusato, so if it's only going to be
one or two bodies, you have a right to you don't want
this body in your
field, so cause this טומאה, Tumah, that seems to be the primary
issue, but who knows,
you just want it out of here, doesn't belong here. So you
basically have a right to disinter and to reinter it in a
cemetery or a more appropriate place if it's one or two bodies.
Thank you. Until you find that there's three bodies, then we're going
to have to be concerned that there's a whole graveyard underneath here.
And then if they're already buried in a graveyard, you don't have
a right to move them from the graveyard they're buried in. You
have to deal with the fact that there's a graveyard underneath your
property and you have to assume basically there's טומאה Tumah all around,
but you do not have a right to what? Could be public
property. Still the road there, whatever. Right. No, we're not saying it's
אסור Asur to use the space above. I want to be clear.
There's not an איסור, Issur, they would use the ground above where
I mean, probably not if the body was buried right at the
surface like a cemetery, but if there was a body buried deep
below ground they would walk on top of these caves. There would
not be a prohibition to use it, but you just don't want
טומאה Tumah there. It keeps כהנים Kohanim out and then it has
all these implications, right? You're going to harvest your wheat and all
those types of things or whatever you're going to use it for.
So if there is so the basic rule is if it's one
or two you can relocate them. If it's three and they're laid
down in a way that indicates they were properly buried, you have
to assume a graveyard and you can't and you can't move it.
And then, B, as we're going to see, once you assume a
graveyard, you're going to have to search in order to try to
figure out the external limits of the graveyard because then not only
can you not move them and there's טומאה Tumah here, there could
be טומאה Tumah all around and you're going to have to do
a search for that. One minute. But if it's one or two
you can move them.
נוטלו ואת תפוסתו, Notlo Ve'et Tefusato, you take it and its what
it grabs onto, meaning the dirt directly under it where some of
the bodily fluids might have run into and there's an idea that
those get buried with the body. And that's what you would do
with one of them. Interesting though the הלכה Halacha is that if
it was not buried properly, if it was like a body had
fallen in a battle had been murdered, you would not actually take
the grounds with it, which is a somewhat of a strange
idea, make up your mind, is it a problem with those bodily
fluids or not? But apparently that's only הלכה Halacha in a case
that a body has been buried. שנים, Shenayim, if it's two, נוטלן
ואת תפוסתן, Notlan Ve'et Tefusan, then again, you remove them and the
ground directly under them and you rebury them. מצא שלושה, Matza Sheloshah,
and here's where it's obviously relevant for us to determine the parameters
of a graveyard. If you found three, then should we assume, who
knows, maybe God forbid it was a caravan passing through and some
bandits attacked them and they had just been buried there because the
caravan had to move on. So you can't necessarily assume three is
a graveyard. But number one, the first indication is that all the
bodies are buried properly. Number two, they're buried at the spacing that
you would expect in a graveyard. So with those combined and there
are three of them, you have to assume that you've got a
graveyard here. מצא שלושה, Matza Sheloshah, then אם יש ביניהן מארבע ועד
שמונה, Im Yesh Beinehen Me'arba Ve'ad Shmoneh, if there is between four
to eight אמות Amot between them, הרי זו שכונת קברות, Harei Zu
Shechunat Kevarot, then this is a neighborhood of graves, it's an area
it's a graveyard or at least an area where there might be
multiple graves.
What? Who would design a graveyard like that? That's a lot of
wasted space. ארבע אמות Arba Amot between them? Oh, so you're right,
it doesn't The way this is being read, I was going to
explain this more, but now I'm realizing just the maybe פשט pshat
way of reading it, the way you're reading it is, it means
that there's four אמות amot between each one, right? The four to
eight אמות amot is being read as the distance from the outer
edge of one to the outer edge of the third. It's the
total distance that contains or that contains all three of these graves
that you have found. But you're right, the language יש ביניהן yesh
benehen sounds almost like the spacing between the individual ones. But it's
being read as like between all of them they take up between
four to eight אמות, amot, הרי זו שכונת קברות. harei zo shechunat
kvarot. ובודק ממנו ולהלן עשרים אמה. ubodek mimeno ulehalan esrim ama. And
you check from there in twenty אמה, ama, presumably in all directions,
we'll talk about this in a minute, but now that you know
that there's a graveyard here maybe there are other graves and you
gotta check. מצא אחד בסוף עשרים אמה, matza echad besof esrim ama,
if you find one at the end of twenty אמה, ama, so
then you know the graveyard went to that point. So then you
have to keep on checking, maybe it goes even further than that
point. Then בודק ממנו ולהלן עשרים אמה, bodek mimeno ulehalan esrim ama,
then from that one you keep on going twenty אמה ama until
you get twenty אמה ama clear where there's no grave, שרגלים לדבר,
sheraglayim ladavar, cause you know you might say give me a break
like if I find one grave twenty אמה ama away from these
three it's reasonable to assume that that's maybe the outer limit of
the graveyard. Okay, but no once you know you've got a graveyard
and once you know that this is part of it then that's
and then that maybe you know maybe there's more graves buried even
further. So once you find one, even one at the end of
twenty אמה, ama, there's some you know we say the thing has
legs. Normally you say the thing has legs means like it's I
don't know it's gonna spread right or something like that. But anyway
but here it means here it means it's there's some substantiating evidence
that indicates that we're dealing with a graveyard and this is part
of it. And once that's true it might even continue further. One
minute, שאילו—שאילו מתחילה מצאו, if you had found a single grave right
by itself you wouldn't and there would be not there you know
even had you dug a little bit around you wouldn't have found
anything. So נוטלו ובתפוסתו, notlo ubitfusato, you would have relocated it. But
now that you found it after having found the first three right
now you have to go ahead and assume it's part of that
graveyard and continue to check even further. Which raises an interesting question
which is let's say the order was different. You dug one and
you found it right and then you kept on digging for other
reasons. You want to know making you know you were uncovering the
ground to lay a foundation of a house or something and then
you found three like somewhere distant right. Does that sort of change
if the you know in terms of where you have to check
and whether you can relocate if the order of discovering them was
different. But we're not going to worry about that. שאילו, she'ilu I
don't understand what the שאילו. she'ilu, It's just of saying like I
recognize the fact that a single grave under other circumstances would not
have been an issue and you would have been able to relocate
it and you would have assumed a single grave, but in this
context you have to interpret it as part of the graveyard and
that the graveyard might continue and therefore it has much different types
of implications finding that single grave. Good point I left that out.
Okay anyway what do you what did you want to say? Jonah,
I was just a little struck before that like you know that
there's no עניין של כבוד המת inyan shel kavod hamet to like
you know the road where you know there's already a graveyard? Did
you say... Yeah, I mean I don't know what to say. I
mean there is but on the other hand you know I don't
it's a good question like
how at what stage do we sort of recognize the space as
a בית הקברות. beit hakevarot. And obviously there's a lot of הלכות
halachot about כבוד kavod in בית הקברות beit hakevarot and so on.
But to what degree do we say this is a buried בית
הקברות beit hakevarot here? It's not a בית הקברות. beit hakevarot. This
is a wheat field that has a בית הקברות beit hakevarot buried
underneath it. So you know and that doesn't demand the same type
of things here. You're just planting wheat and there happens to be
a בית הקברות beit hakevarot buried below right? So... so I don't
know exactly like when you say the difference. I mean to my
mind the obvious difference is is it ניכר, nikar, you walk in
and the nature of the space is one thing or the other.
But yeah, but... like in Israel today when they discover they're going
to build a building? Yeah we mentioned that yesterday. You always have
to call in the Department of Antiquities. But aren't there people like
orthodox groups who protest? Oh when they find when they find bones?
Oh the digging itself because they just say you you're definitely gonna
hit graves. Yeah they say they're going to move it and they
say you can't move it you know and... well that would be
that's a good point I should have brought that in. I mean
I don't know exactly when those groups protest but certainly if it's
like you know if if the government is trying to build some
building or whatever and they find some graves they'll move those bones
but they're not going to care if it's one grave or two
graves or five graves right you know? And according to this right
once it's three graves you have to leave it undisturbed. I don't
know if those groups would protest even one or two. They might
for all I know. But according to this right once it's three
graves you gotta leave it. They're not allowed to move it. Right
exactly exactly. But then it gets to Michael's point so let the
government say okay we won't move it we'll leave them there and
then we'll build on top of it. Right but apparently they can't
leave them there either because they're like digging to create a foundation
or whatever you know they're digging up the space. It's not just
leaving it below. Okay so now let me say something here about
this four to eight issue
because where does the four to eight number come from and how
does it fit into our previous discussion? Okay because our
previous... So if you remember, right, we were sort of assuming. Now,
the funny thing is, and I would have read this that this
is talking about burial under the ground and it is not talking
about a cave. First of all, if you, like, hit a cave
and then you know, you know, you go into the cave, you
sort of see what its parameters are and you sort of see
what it looks like and so on. And it doesn't sound like
you're dealing with having discovered a cave under the ground. And then
like it has nothing to do with our subject, you know, it
would be a normal burial in the ground. And again, from what
everything I've read, even in Israel where they had these caves and
the niches in the caves and these ossuaries, that was for the
wealthy. Normal people had a straight burial in the ground. So I
would have said this משנה mishna has nothing to do with our
discussion. But the גמרא Gemara seems to feel that it does. And
if that's true, what's the idea of having three graves within four
to eight אמות? amot? Because before, if you remember, before we were
assuming an אמה ama between them and an אמה ama for each
one, so that's three graves in five אמות, amot, not in four
אמות. amot. Okay, now, so three graves in eight you could understand,
right? Because if you have some walls had, depending on whether you,
you know, you said that the cave was six by four or
whatever, you know, you, so if not all the niches were filled,
you know, you could have three graves in eight אמות. amot. Okay,
but you could also have three graves in twelve אמות amot or
whatever. But anyway, we're worried about them in a minute. But where
do you get the three graves in four אמות? amot? Okay? Because
that should really be in five. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says that
this approach assumes that you have less than an אמה ama between
the graves. That this approach assumes... well, it was a מחלוקת machlokas
רשב"ם Rashbam and רמב"ם... Rambam... it was a מחלוקת machlokas in the
גמרא, Gemara, they say. Anyway, so this approach assumes that you have
basically like a half of an אמה ama between the graves, or
he even says like maybe even less. So that's how you can
get three graves within like four אמות. amot. תוספות Tosafot has a
better answer. תוספות Tosafot says maybe we're talking about at the corner.
So now of course it might depend how you found the graves.
Okay, but here if there is, remember we said there was a
half אמה ama at the corner, right? So here, right, within this,
I mean, you know, I'm not exactly sure how we're sort of
like drawing the line, but you know, like you draw a line
like that, right, it's like one, two, three, four... wait, one... right,
one, two, three... but the angle is different than the... yeah, three
and a half, right, or it's a little less than four and
then you start and then you bump into the third grave. Hmm.
So this would, does that really make it better? Because it says
one... if this was... yeah, because here... wait, one, two, three, four.
Here you've finished four and you haven't yet found, hit into the
next grave. Right? So you could, you could count four אמות amot
and you would not have, you would not have three graves. Whereas
here, here, once even within four אמות, amot, you're going to hit
into the next grave, right? One, two, three... wouldn't it be better
to take away the space at the corner? Yeah, but based on
the way they were reading the earlier גמרא, Gemara, they were assuming
that there was a little margin at the corner. Okay, so that's
the question about that. Now, eight... so I'm going to get to
it. So that's the four אמות. amot. Now how do you deal
with the eight? So the first thing that we have to assume,
and this is also why this debate is important, is the first
thing we have to assume is that we're talking according to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, right? Because according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon the,
the sides of the grave were six by eight. So if it
was six by eight, right, and then within that, of course he
said that you would have, how many did he say you would
have here? Four, right? So within eight אמות amot you would get
four, not three. But they might not all be filled. Okay, so
that's why, so you can have three within eight, right? Maybe you
didn't find one, maybe they're not all filled. Well, three within even
more. Right, exactly. But then we don't start worrying about it as
much. Okay, I mean, well, the reason we don't worry about it
more is again, because, and this is why the eight is important,
because the caves wouldn't be bigger than eight. So since the caves
wouldn't be bigger than eight, right, I mean, still it'd be bizarre,
what are you doing with three bodies in ten אמות, amot, but
it would not be this type of a, you know, we would
not assume... now again, it's also funny because our משנה mishna is
dealing with minimums, right? The minimum or the standards. If you had
a big cave and a big family or whatever, you're not restricted
to only use up to eight אמות. amot. So I also don't
fully get it. But anyway, since it sounds like the standard is
eight אמות, amot, so they don't have to assume they're all filled.
So therefore three within eight makes sense. More than eight doesn't make
sense because it's what do you call it, because it's, because again,
somehow that wouldn't be the standard. So even if they're not all
filled or maybe they're just not close enough to have to necessarily
draw that assumption. Okay, so that's why we say between eight, we
say eight because of the size of the cave according to רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. This is following רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. And we
say four because again, you know, within what, you, you know, you
almost get it this way, or maybe you assume a slightly smaller
space, or maybe with the corner, so you can get to... Three
within four. So that's why the minimum is four, I mean the
distance, more compressed than that we would say who knows, like I
said maybe some bandits attack the caravan and they were all thrown
in together, it's not a normal layout. Okay, you're allowed to move
the hundred bodies there, you're allowed to move? Yeah, because it's not
a graveyard. Because it's not a graveyard, so you're allowed to move.
That's הלכה, Halacha, yeah, you're right. Okay, so more if they're more
condensed than if they're not laid out with the natural spacing of
a graveyard and therefore yes, even if like it was a tragedy
or whatever you would be allowed to rebury them and, but you
know, but at that, so that's why they, four is like the
minimum, any less than that would be too condensed, but a normal
layout you could have three within four and more than eight, you
don't assume that they were all together, since the, since according to
ר׳ שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, the standard maximum size of a cave would
be eight. Okay, yes David. Is there any custom although it doesn't
seem to be here, that the body has to be laid in
a certain direction? Yes, תוספות Tosfos says there was. You mean feet
first or head first? No, I mean in terms of north, south,
east, west. Oh, no, because these bodies are laid these ways, these
bodies are laid that way. Yeah, okay, so I didn't know if
there was any. Doesn't seem to be. But that's interesting, yeah let's
say one was laid one way, the other laid another way. Yeah,
so that's an interesting question you would want to know, is the
head first or feet first and if they were all laid in
a consistent way, what does that sort of tell you about the
layout? Right there's more like in, there obviously would be
more details that would give you an indication of what you're looking
at, which the משנה's Mishna not spelling out. Yes. I'm just guessing
but that four by eight is four within eight or it's dimension?
Well right now the four to eight we're saying that if they're,
if there's three bodies within four אמות, amos, not like width and
or vertical and horizontal. No,
it's, it's, it's straight like ground, length on the ground. If there
are three bodies buried within, within a four אמות amos length of
ground,
not smaller than four אמות amos because that's too condensed to be
a graveyard and not more spread out than eight, then they're not
considered,
what? The width here is four, right? The width, you mean this?
Yeah, but we're not talking about that. That's one body. We're talking
about how many bodies can you find within right four אמות. amos.
And if it's in a line, if it's found like a T,
it'd be different. Right, so that's all the question, what if it's
found this way, does that indicate a graveyard or not? So there's
obviously missing information here. Now, the other question is, what's the where
does the twenty אמות amos come from? And this is going to
be addressed in the גמרא Gemara to some degree. Okay, and here
the idea is, is that we're going to assume, okay,
right, this sort of setup. Okay, so if we're assuming this setup
and we're going like ר׳ שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, okay, that says like
the six by eight, okay. So,
so,
you found a, you found three graves. Now you don't know, did
the three graves you found, were they these three or were they
these three, right, or obviously whatever that would be the same. Which
wall were they on? In case they were in this wall, there
might be other graves in the opposite wall down here. So you
have to check, right, eight and six, you remember this is six
by six and eight, that's twenty-two for all you math wizards, not
twenty. So we're going to have to see about that in the
גמרא, Gemara, but you're going to have to check at the end
of twenty-two אמות amos to see if there's other, if there's other
graves. Okay, so that's checking twenty אמות amos in at least one
direction. All right, but the משנה Mishna sounds like you have to
check twenty אמות amos in all directions. But you don't know which
one you found first. Right, so first of all by the way,
as you're checking here, you're checking, you know, you're not just saying
I'm going to go twenty אמות amos later and then check there.
Because, you know, you don't know exactly anyway what you're looking at,
but you know, even if you're looking at this, you know, there
could be graves buried all along here. So you're checking, checking, checking
all along up through and then there's graves, could be graves here
and graves here and graves over there. So you're checking twenty אמות
amos in that direction. Now, why do you have to go in
the other two directions? Because maybe you're not looking at this wall,
maybe you're looking at this wall. So if you're looking at this
wall, right, if you're looking here at this wall, so you would
certainly have to check this way, you know, because then there would
be like other bodies there. But why would you have to check
more than eight אמות? amos? No, because the point is you don't
know which one you're in. I know, but the point is it
could be tilted by forty-five degrees. All right, so but okay, I'm
telling you the, okay fine, but you can figure it out there's
a limit to the possibilities if we're assuming a normal type of
a layout like this. So okay, but then why do you have
to, so you have to check twenty אמות amos this way, but
why twenty אמות amos that way? So the רשב״ם Rashbam says well
if you continue with this idea that it was this wall that
you discovered, etc., so when you get to here, again if we're
assuming ר׳ שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, right, so then you've got another cave
there of eight אמות, amos, okay, right, so then you've got... And
you're checking here. Now, it's not exactly 20, okay, but because again
you don't know the exact configuration, right, you could be going all
the way up to like 16 אמות amos in this direction. All
right, and similarly, and here's where you would say like which way
are they buried, feet or head first, because that might tell you
which wall you're looking at. But similarly the three you found might
have been like this wall. Wait a minute, I don't understand the
eight in that direction because you have to go to the end
of one. Well, eight, and then eight, you'll find the next one
within eight. What? Between here, between the end of one. No, no,
maybe you're not finding everything, maybe some things are not buried in
it, but maybe there's something here or here, right? All
right, so is there anywhere that we have an example of even
remotely close to all this? I have no idea. That's what I
was asked the other day. Like I would like to see archaeological
like schematics and to see... I mean, it's not perfectly... it's got
a courtyard... I know, those pictures were very helpful, but like I
need a schematic, you know, for like the סנהדרין Sanhedrin in Jerusalem,
also but... Yeah,
I don't know either. This all seems to be very theoretical, but
right, otherwise you have to go with topographical
features and... Right, exactly, that's like the משנה Mishna said, הכל לפי
הקרקע, Hakol lefi hakarka, you know. So I—whatever, this is all very
abstract. Anyway, that would get you at least 16 אמות amos in
this direction. Again, also you might be dealing with like these three
when you found three, so that would get you sort of like,
you know, 16 אמות amos in that direction. So it's not exactly
20 by 20 in all sides, okay, but this is the basic
point since you don't know which three you're dealing with, and given
this type of a layout, you have to go like 20
אמות, amot, you know, in various directions. Of course, like if somebody's
paying attention, it's like, still doesn't make a lot of sense because...
because you're still going... the direction you have to go is determined
more by like the way the מת meis is pointing, right? If
the מת meis is pointing this way, it's 20 אמות amos along
the line of the מת. meis. If the מת meis is pointing
this way, right, so it's also like, you know, 20 אמות amos
along the... anyway, it doesn't exactly explain why it's like 20 אמות
amos in all directions regardless of the way the מת meis is
pointing, but that's basically the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it, okay?
You can certainly see why you have to go 20 אמות amos
in this direction, right, because if you have this type of a
setup, right, then you could... yeah. I'm probably missing something here, but
why when you find a body buried in the ground are you
using the cave configuration to determine... Yeah, so that's what I said
at the beginning and that's what I said yesterday. Like, I have
no idea. The משנה Mishna does not say you found a cave.
A cave you would think would be, you know, its sort of
its structure would be more like self-evident that you're looking at a
cave and a burial crypt and so on. And most of the
times they were dealing with burial in the ground, not in the
cave. So why the גמרא Gemara maps this משנה, Mishna, which seems
to be dealing with straight like an in-the-ground graveyard, to assumptions about
caves and that we're dealing with that, I have no idea. I
just don't know. I mean, again, I don't know if any of
your notes talk about it. You know, it seems like the גמרא
Gemara is almost assuming like everybody was buried in this type of
a configuration, but you know, but certainly not what we see in
other places. So I really don't know why we're assuming that that's
what we're doing. If you don't find that square, then why go
further south there? I mean, if you're going, you know, why go
further down? If you don't find the... let's say you find the
three on your first three that you found, right? Yeah, okay, or
even ones to the left, right? And then you see... so you're
saying we have to go all the way down, going down, down,
down, you're checking along the side here. If you don't find that
six-by-six area... Well, what do you mean? You found it. Or as
you're digging, all you're finding is dirt. Okay, you know what I'm
saying? You don't see an area... you're like saying like, is it
paved or not. That's similar to the question like, you should be
finding a cave here. But you didn't find a cave, right? So
I don't really... I can't really explain this, right? We're sort of
like assuming the configuration of a cave even though the reality assumes
that you're just digging and finding dirt, you know. All right, so
anyway, that's but that's the basic way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains A:
the within four to eight, and B: why you're checking 20 אמות.
amot. Okay, let me just check one... let me just reread one
line here in the רשב"ם. Rashbam. Wait let me just... I just
want to make sure I got
all
this right. בשנים beshanim כדאמרן kid'amarn ובשלושה uvishlosha הקבורים hakvurim
כסדרן kesidran
של שמונה shel shemona וצריך לבדוק v'tzarich livdok הימנה. heimena.
Okay, so what the רשב"ם Rashbam is sort of...
yeah, no, I think I said that right.
Yeah, I said that right. Okay, fine, I said that right. Okay,
now I'll say one last thing about the way the רשב"ם Rashbam
says it, which is that he says this also helps explaining the
line in the משנה Mishnah that said that if you find a
single one at twenty אמות, Amot, you have to check another twenty
אמות, Amot, which makes it sound like, come on, and then it
says like, oh, because there's some רגלים לדבר, Reglayim Ladavar, some substantiation.
So the רשב"ם Rashbam says the reason it is saying that, or
maybe he doesn't, maybe תוספות Tosafot does, is that in this scenario,
let's say you found something at the end of twenty אמות, Amot,
right? You would actually say, great, I'm going to stop here. That
is a complete
grave cave complex. It goes from here to here and it doesn't
go beyond that, right? Why would I have to go further? I
mean, if you're dealing with like burial in a grave, so you
keep on finding, you keep on checking, you don't know where it
ends. But if you're dealing with a cave complex, why do you
have to check after you've found a group over here? So the
point of the משנה Mishnah is, yes, if it was just that,
you might say you can stop. But once we know you've got
one cave complex, for all we know, you've got yet another cave
complex. And maybe the thing you found at the end of twenty
אמות Amot is not the end of this cave complex, maybe it's
the beginning of another cave and its set of burial. So that's
like the point of the משנה. Mishnah. If you find another thing
at the end of twenty אמות, Amot, we're having you check twenty
אמות Amot because we're assuming like one unit here and you check
within that area. But once you find it, you can't stop and
say that's the end of—again, if we're reading this through the lens
of the cave, not through the lens of a basic graveyard. You
can't stop and say that's the end, a cave doesn't go further
than this. No, now you have to be concerned that maybe it's
part of a different set of caves, and now you have to
keep on checking. Yes. So in that case, you're checking twenty אמות
Amot backwards? Right. What... if you found these... now that's the thing
the רשב"ם Rashbam doesn't explain, which is, why do I have to
also check up twenty אמות? Amot? Unless what? Unless there might be
another cave there. Right, but we don't start by having to assume
another cave, because then why twenty אמות? Amot? Why not check a
hundred אמות? Amot? You know, who knows? There might be other caves
in the area. So you start by assuming like there's this cave
and its graves, and you sort of check twenty אמות Amot in
all directions, because that's what would be with one cave complex. But
if you find one, then you have to assume, okay, great, now
I've found one, but I can't be certain it's part of this
complex, maybe it's part of another. But you don't have to worry
about that initially, right? Because then there would be no limit to
how much you would have to check. Is that not clear? I
mean, it's strange. You're right. Why I start searching assuming one cave
complex, and if I find it, then I have to say, okay,
but now I don't know for sure, maybe it's part of another
cave complex? I can't assume it's part of the first one. Wait,
so I guess I'm understanding that like why
the reason we know to go that way is because of the
direction. So that's the thing. So what this explains is why you
go twenty אמות Amot in those three directions, right? It doesn't... but
presumably, and again, like you would say it depends which way the
body is buried, which direction to go, but we're presumably not looking
at which is head first and feet first and so on. So
it sounds like you would also have to go twenty אמות Amot
in that direction because maybe this is the back wall. Right. So
exactly. So then since this might be the back wall of the
bottom, right, so now that's why you're now going in twenty אמות
Amot in all three directions, because you don't know exactly where in
the cave complex it is. But regardless, you know, it's not going
to be within one complex, it's not going to be any, you
know, it's not going to be beyond twenty. But once you find
it, you can't be certain it's part of the same complex and
you have to do yet another. Yes, yes. You are going... I
forgot to draw it. Yes, but you are going in all. But
again, what this also assumes is you can't tell by which feet
first, head first, and so on, which is a little strange that
you can't use that as evidence. Okay, so let's keep on going.
Again, all of this is just because the גמרא Gemara is insisting
on reading this through the lens of the cave burial and not
a ground burial. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר מר, Amar Mar, מארבע ועד שמונה
מני, Me'arba Ve'ad Shmona Mani, who's this going like? Four by eight.
אי רבנן, I Rabbanan, האמרי ארבע אמות על שש. Ha'amri Arba Amot
Al Shesh.
You're not going to have three bodies. Here you see that the
גמרא Gemara is reading this through the lens of the caves. Okay,
so so what to go? Who had this? Plato? The metaphor of
the cave? Whatever. Anyway, all right. So anyway, if it's the רבנן,
Rabbanan, so you don't have... you don't have a length of a
wall more than six. So you're not going to get three within
eight. Three would have to be within six, you know. Now, of
course, the funny thing is that's a minimum, is that a maximum?
The rabbis didn't believe you ever had, you know, cave walls that
long? But okay, that's what it's saying. אי ר' שמעון, I Rabbi
Shimon,
if it's רב שמעון Rav Shimon who has a cave wall eight
אמות Amot and you could— Normally you'd get four in eight, but
maybe again one of them wasn't filled, so you get three in
eight. אי רבי שמעון האמר שש שמונה. Ee Rabbi Shimon ha'amar shesh
shmoneh. So
it's six by eight. Now what, so why is that a question?
So the way the Rashbam sort of reads the question is, he
reads the Gemara, I mean Tosafot sort of would read it a
little differently, but he reads the Gemara, where are we getting the
idea of four by eight? Why don't we say either you find
three bodies in six, or you find three bodies in eight, like
maybe one isn't filled? Why did we say three bodies within four?
Now again Tosafot sort of said that maybe we're dealing around the
corner, but anyway, the way the Rashbam reads it, that's the question
at this stage. We get that you can have three bodies within
eight, we get you can have three bodies within six, but where
do we get this idea that you could have three bodies within
four according to Rabbi Shimon? So it says, so the Gemara says,
לעולם רבי שמעון היא והאי תנא הוא, L'olam Rabbi Shimon hee v'hai
tana hoo, it's the following תנא Tana that has different sort of
dimensions of a cave. דתניא מצאן רצופים ואין ביניהן מארבע אמות ועד
שמונה. D'tanya matzanu retzufin v'ein beinehen me'arba amot v'ad shmoneh.
If you found them, you know, really tightly packed, and they're not
between four to eight. There's more than three, three bodies in in
less than four אמות, amot, which really has to mean like unless
they're in the same hole or whatever, really has to mean like
what, like one אמה amah to a body, like really like you
know lined up very tightly against one another. Okay. So less than,
you know, not four to eight, meaning either more spread out or
more compact. Okay.
ואין ביניהן V'ein beinehen and that's what רצופים retzufin means, more compressed,
מארבע ועד שמונה יש להן תפוסה, me'arba v'ad shmoneh yesh lahen tefusah,
so again you would, you would, you would disinter them and re
and rebury them elsewhere with the ground underneath them. ואין להן שכונת
קברות, V'ein lahen shechunat kvarot, but they're not considered to be a
graveyard and you would be allowed even with three bodies to move
them because they're more compact. רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Shimon, Rabbi Shimon ben
Yehuda says in the name of Rabbi Shimon: רואין את האמצעין כאילו
אינם. Ro'in et ha'emtza'in ke'ilu einam. No no no. If they're more
compact, then that does not that's not a reason to say it's
not a graveyard. If you have let's say four bodies, right, right
next to each other, very compact, okay, so and they're all within
I don't know, let's say let's say this is here,
this is four אמות, amot, okay, and this is another אמה. amah.
So that's five. So it's a total of
five. Okay. So you'd say, oh, it's more compact, any three bodies
is in, you know, is in less than four אמות. amot. Okay,
whatever, 3.9.
Right? Any four bodies is within less than four any three bodies
is less than four אמות, amot, so therefore it's not a graveyard.
That's the תנא קמא's Tana Kamma position. Rabbi Shimon comes and says,
so okay, eliminate one of the bodies, you know.
So too packed isn't a problem, because you can always make too
packed less packed. Ignore one of the bodies and you've got three
bodies now that are within four, right, that are within four, you
know, that are within four אמות, amot, so now so now it
is a graveyard. So the question so we're going to see about
that later because the whole point is seems to be if they're
more compact it shows that they were sort of put there, you
know, in an emergency situation, they're not being laid out with proper
spacing. So how can you say just pretend one of the bodies
isn't there and now they got the right spacing? Okay, so we'll
worry about that later, but for what us is right now important
is that he says that this is Rabbi Shimon who is now
quoted to be embracing this four by eight dimension. So the Gemara
says you see there's an approach of Rabbi Shimon that says not
six by eight, but apparently four by eight. Okay. So the Gemara
says, והשתא מצטרף מארבע ועד שמונה. v'ashtah mitztaref me'arba v'ad shmoneh. Okay,
so fine. So now we've explained that the eight number comes because
that's the length of the wall for Rabbi Shimon, and the four
becomes even though this should be six because apparently there is a
Rabbi Shimon out there that says four. For the Rashbam that means
that he would understand that the wall of a cave is actually
only four. Tosafot says again it has more to do with assuming
that we can look at the possibility of getting getting three including
a corner. But anyway, that's where we get the four by eight.
So now the Gemara says like
this: דמאי אוקימתא כרבי שמעון. D'ma'i okimta k'Rabbi Shimon. So you're saying
we're assuming Rabbi Shimon in this whole case about the finding these
graves. אימא סיפא בודק הימנו ולהלן עשרים אמה. Eima seifa: bodek heimenu
u'le'halan esrim amah.
So then you check 20 אמה. amah. And now we're going to
get with the problem one minute. You'd have to check 22. Eight
and six and eight is, right, 22. So why do you stop
and actually has it go a little bit more because you have
to get into the wall of the next cave. So if it's
Rabbi Shimon where does this 20 number come from? Now of course
even if it's the רבנן Rabbanan where does the 20 number come
from? But
within Rabbi Shimon. Okay. אימא סיפא בודק הימנו ולהלן עשרים אמה מני
Eima seifa: bodek heimenu u'le'halan esrim amah. Mani? Who's that going like?
אי רבי שמעון עשרים ותרתין הויין. Ee Rabbi Shimon esrim v'tarten havyan.
It's 22. It's not 20. אי רבנן תמני סרי הויין. Ee Rabbanan
tmoneh esrei havyan. Now according to the רבנן Rabbanan it also doesn't
work because it would be six and six and six and that'd
be 18. So where are you getting the number 20? Yes.
אי רבי שמעון. Ee Rabbi Shimon. Oh,
psh, I don't know why the גמרא Gemara didn't suggest that. No,
that's
no, first thing I was going to say is just because the
cave is narrow doesn't mean the courtyard, but to the degree that
it's, right, I mean, again, you could sort of imagine, right, a
wider opening and a wider courtyard with a leading into a narrow
cave, but it's a very reasonable read. Yeah, I don't know why
the גמרא Gemara didn't suggest it. יישר כח. Shkayach. All right.
I've got to look around, maybe one of the ראשונים Rishonim suggested,
but it's a really good idea. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like
this:
Okay, אי רבי שמעון עשרין ותרתין הוויין, iy Rabbi Shimon esrin ve-tartin
havyan, it's 22. אי רבנן תמני סרי הוויין. iy Rabbanan tamnei srei
havyan. לעולם רבנן היא, le-olam Rabbanan hee, it's the רבנן. Rabbanan. וכגון
דבדק באלכסונא. u-kh’gon de-vadak be-alakhsona. So it says, okay, forget it, it's
not רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it's the רבנן. Rabbanan. Now, and therefore
this wall is only six. Now of course what the רשב"ם Rashbam
then says is, wait a minute, we're now going to say that
this wall is six to help us get to the 20 number,
then how come we're saying three bodies within eight? You should say
three bodies within six. So we're going to like ignore that problem
right now, okay? Like there's a lot of things that are very
confusing here. But anyway, but right now let's just focus on the
20 number. So how's it going to help that we're dealing with
six? That should be 18. So the גמרא Gemara says no, because
what you're doing is you're actually checking here at an angle. Now,
why are you checking at and what we're going to assume is,
well, we'll get to the math in a minute, but we're going
to assume that if you check at an angle here, this is
six by four, this angle is going to be eight. Okay, so
we'll get to that math in a minute. But eight plus six
plus and then you go straight. So we're going to discuss in
a minute why you're doing an angle and then straight, but eight
plus six plus six is going to be—do I get the math
right?—20. Okay, now, why are you checking—besides why did you do part
an angle and part straight—why are you checking at an angle? So
the reason you're checking at an angle is because you don't know
exactly like where you are. Are you in open space and so
on? And where you might actually be is, you might actually be—I'm
trying to realize remember how—oh, the רשב"ם Rashbam says yes, he says
because not only is this four wide, you know what else is
four wide? The bodies are buried four deep into the niche, right?
So what the רשב"ם Rashbam says is, is that you check because
maybe you're here—again, like I would think it would matter whether where
you which of these things you're at. Anyway, I'm not totally getting
this, but this is the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says. Maybe you're
here and so you're checking, you know, as you're checking down here,
right, you're trying to check are there bodies? So you found these
three. Now what you're going to have to do is you're not—what
are you going to do? It's actually this space is like the
least you're concerned with. What you're concerned with is the stuff off
to the sides, right? So as you're checking down here, you're really
going to be checking the, you know, at the edges here you're
going to be checking the wall. At this edge you're going to
go down and check this wall, at this edge you're going to
go down and check this wall, assuming you're looking at this configuration.
So what the רשב"ם Rashbam says is, is that you want to
be extra careful, and if you just go straight, you might not
catch something, you know, because who knows? Maybe there's
a—what would you be concerned about? Well I guess if you would
go straight down like this, then maybe there's like a little body,
a נפל nefel buried like that and you wouldn't catch it, okay?
And if you go straight down like this, I don't know, maybe
one body is very, very deep and you wouldn't catch it. So
what you're going to do is you're going to check like that.
Okay, so this is six and the bodies are buried four deep
and that way you have like at an angle at least what
he argues is you have a greater chance of hitting, of finding
bodies. I don't know if that's actually true, because—on both sides? Yeah,
apparently that's what he says. You sort of do that on both
sides. Is that really true though that you have a greater chance?
I mean you do cover a little bit more distance, but is
that exactly clear to me why that gives you a greater chance
of hitting bodies? Greater chance if they're all buried at the same
depth but you don't know what that depth is? Right, it's just
like—oh right, so not like I said one is whatever. Maybe they
all start a little bit further down. Oh that's a good point.
If they all start a little bit further in then you'll hit
one of them when you get down here. And if they're all
very close then you'll hit it at the top. Yeah, that's a
good point. Then once you hit it you should switch directions and
then go straight. All right, anyway that's the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer. That's
how you get it to not be six but to be eight.
Now let's talk about the math. How is it—is it true
that—that six by four will give you a line of eight? So,
you know, the question is can we use the גמרא'ס Gemara's argument?
The גמרא Gemara says every one by one is like 1.4 this
way.
So the רשב"ם—right, Rashbam you know, that's the square root of
two. as five by five.
Okay, so five by five, right, six by four, five by five,
it gets ten. So five by five times one point four is
seven. So seven is two more than five. So you see that?
So if seven is two more than a five by five, then
by six by four, this is going to be two more than
six and it's going to be eight.
So תוספות Tosafot proves it's great. So it's like how would you
prove that's not right? So you could always just apply a formula,
but how do you prove it's not right if you've got a
formula? So תוספות Tosafot proves it's not right because תוספות Tosafot basically,
if you see there's a picture in תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot basically
says like this. תוספות Tosafot says, okay, תוספות Tosafot says look, I'm
going to prove to you that it's not eight.
Because if this is six, it's four by here's the four by
four. So what's this? That's four by four or whatever, so if
you multiply that by one point four, it's five point six, right?
Yes, everybody with me? Right, and then he says go straight down,
right, that's another two, right? So that's seven point six. That's not
eight. And this, תוספות Tosafot says, is definitely more than that.
So you can't tell me this, right, is eight if this is
seven point six. It's pretty good, pretty impressive without any formula they
show that the רשב"ם Rashbam is wrong. Do people sort of see
that? Right? And how did he get the five point six
in the middle? Oh, because the גמרא Gemara knows that that if
they're even sides, the diagonal is one point four any side. So
a six by four, you have a four by four here, which
is five point six, right? And then plus two is seven point
six, so don't tell me a six by four, that's going to
be eight. Okay, now what actually is it? Wait, you said it's
one point four? One point four times the side. So four by
four, one point four times four, that's five point six.
It's the square root of two. Anything that's X and X, the
diagonal is one point four times X. Right? So four by four,
that's five point six.
So six by four, it's got to be less than seven point
six.
That's תוספות. Tosafot. By the way, does anyone remember the formula? I
am embarrassed to admit, this is really embarrassing to admit, I forgot
the basic formula of a right angle. Okay, anybody remember? One squared,
one squared...
Yeah, I mean once I realized it, oh duh, of course, anyway.
So a squared plus b squared equals c squared, so it's the
square root of a squared plus b squared is this, and I
think it's about seven point two or something like that, I forgot,
I did the math. Point two or something... what? Okay, anyway, alright,
so so it doesn't exactly work. That the גמרא Gemara sort of
says, we went from six to eight, תוספות Tosafot points out that
the רשב"ם Rashbam got the math wrong, but it doesn't exactly explain
how it answers what's going on in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's keep
on reading. He suggested I think it's suggested we may have been
discussing
the area of... Chazzan asked why they don't go through the midpoint
where the distance might be like that, to be shorter than the
diagonal. Yeah, yeah.
Okay. Alright, so anyway, but that's the גמרא's Gemara answer. It was
eighteen, but we added two because of going by the diagonal. So
now the גמרא Gemara says,
the גמרא Gemara says like this: והא מאי קסבר—so Ve-ha mai kasavar
the גמרא Gemara says, ומדהא באלכסונא האי נמי באלכסונא עשרים וסרתי הויין.
U-mi-de-ha be-alachsona hai nami be-alachsona esrim ve-sartei havyan.
So according to that, says the גמרא, Gemara, okay, but if somehow
we got eight by going like this—תוספות Tosafot proved the רשב"ם's Rashbam
math was wrong, but he doesn't tell you how we got eight.
But anyway, somehow we got eight here, you should be doing eight
you should be doing it when you get down here too. And
then again we should be back to twenty-two. Why do you start
with the diagonal and then go straight? So it says: חדא באלכסונא
אמרינן תרתי באלכסונא לא אמרינן. Chada be-alachsona amrinan tartei be-alachsona lo amrinan.
No,
we don't demand that you do both תרתי tarteis at a diagonal.
You're going to be, well you understand it, where you found the
graves, you're going to assume that the diagonal is, covers more ground
and is more helpful at discovering things, you're going to demand that
closer to the graves you found and not necessarily as distant. That's
answer number one, how we got twenty. רב ששת Rav Sheshet בריה
דרב אידי אמר—רב ששת son of רב אידי Rav Idi says: לעולם
רבי שמעון היא, Le-olam Rabbi Shimon hi, it is רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. Okay,
so it's רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, we're back to eight. So if
it's eight and six and eight, we should be at twenty-two. How
does it only, how was it only twenty? לעולם רבי שמעון היא
והכא במאי עסקינן בנפלי. Le-olam Rabbi Shimon hi ve-hacha be-mai askinan bi-nefili.
So this is what we mentioned earlier. Here apparently it's saying that
originally you found
only some infant graves here. Okay, so if you found only infant
graves in that, you're going to assume that there's only that this
whole... cave is devoted to infant graves, which is a funny idea
because you would still think you would want to bury parents by
their children and families together. But anyway if you're assuming this whole
cave is infant graves, presumably it would not be eight אמות, amos,
then it could be smaller and it could be six אמות. amos.
Okay so גמרא Gemara says like this. ומדהוה בנפילי הא נמי בנפילי?
umidehava b'nefili ha nami b'nefili? So then okay why do we have
to check the other one eight אמות? amos? Why not just assume
all the graves around here are for are for infants? So there's
an obvious answer. תמני סרי הוו? tamni sarei havu? It's only 18?
No. חדא בנפילי אמרינן תרתי בנפילי לא אמרינן. chada b'nefili amrinan tarti
b'nefili la amrinan. We're not going to assume that everything is just
infant graves. Okay so now we have somewhat explained why you're doing
the 20 אמות. amos. Again all of this assuming the bizarre assumption
that you're dealing with finding a cave complex and not straight graves
in the ground. All right now we're going to get to the
last part of that משנה, Mishnah,
which is the what do you call it? Which is you find
three four graves three you know two compressed. You find graves all
you know within צפוף, tzafuf, you know four graves within four אמות.
amos. So that's two compressed and therefore it's not a graveyard. But
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says no, pretend one of them isn't there
and then it's the right spacing or acceptable spacing. So גמרא Gemara
says like this: ורמי דרבנן אדרבנן ורמי דרבי שמעון אדרבי שמעון. v'rami
d'rabbanan a'drabbanan v'rami d'Rebbi Shimon a'Rebbi Shimon.
This question of can you like ignore things if it's too much
is it seems to be that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon and the
רבנן rabbanan take the flip position in another case. What's the case?
דתנן. d'tenan. כרם הנטוע. kerem hanatu'a.
We've dealt with this before. You've got a vineyard and if the
vineyard has the right spacing between the vines then it's considered to
be a vineyard and for laws of כלאים kilayim how close can
you plant other seeds? Okay if it's too compressed they're considered to
be single vines and not a vineyard. So let's say it's and
the spacing is four אמות amot between the vines. So let's say
you have one that is too tight, too compressed. כרם הנטוע פחות
מארבע אמות. kerem hanatu'a pachot m'arba amot. Fewer than four אמות amot
between the vines. So רבי שמעון אומר Rebbi Shimon omer אינו כרם.
eino kerem. It's not a vineyard, it's too compressed. וחכמים אומרים הרי
זה כרם ורואין את האמצעיים כאילו אינם. v'Chachamim omrim harei zeh kerem
v'ro'in et ha'emtza'iyim k'ilu einam. Take out the extra ones and pretend
they're not there. So it's ממש, mamash, I mean okay obviously it's
bizarre that we're talking about graves and vineyards, but again it really
is interesting. It's the same רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon and the חכמים
Chachamim and their positions are flipped. Here the חכמים Chachamim say ignore
the extra and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says you don't ignore the
extra. So what's the different logic? So גמרא Gemara says well there
is different logic. גמרא Gemara says like this. קשיא דרבנן אדרבנן קשיא
דרבי שמעון אדרבי שמעון. kashya d'rabbanan a'drabbanan kashya d'Rebbi Shimon a'Rebbi Shimon.
דרבי שמעון אדרבי שמעון לא קשיא. d'Rebbi Shimon a'Rebbi Shimon la kashya.
No it's not difficult. So by the graveyard he says you ignore
the extra, not by the vineyard. התם לא נטע איניש אדעתא למיעקר.
hatam lo nata inish ada'ata l'me'ekar.
Why would people be planting an extra vine? You don't plant something
you're planning on pulling out of the ground. So therefore we can't
ignore it. It was intentional. You're a bizarre person, you don't know
never learned the first thing about maintaining vineyards, okay, but we don't
say that it was like accidental. It was intentional and therefore we
can't ignore it and it's not the right spacing of a vineyard
and therefore it's not a vineyard. Okay because but that was intentional.
הכא hacha but by the grave זימנין דמשתרמי ליה בין השמשות. zimnin
d'mishtarmi lei bein hashmashot.
You're going and you're you know you got to bury a body
and it's ערב שבת, erev shabbos, you're rushed, ומקרי ומנח ליה umikrei
u'manach lei and you just bury it. Yes it's not like the
exact right place but you know sometimes emergencies happen and you have
to do something and the implication being your intention would be to
come back when you had more time and to disinter it and
to move it to a more appropriate place. So therefore you can
pretend that it's not there because maybe there was one extra thing
that was put there unintentionally or not with a sense of being
permanent and it doesn't define the space. So you can imagine that
one thing there is is unintended in a certain way or unintended
to remain there. So that's his position why you can ignore, you
know, pretend one is not there. דרבנן אדרבנן נמי לא קשיא. d'rabbanan
a'drabbanan nami la kashya. And the רבנן rabbanan would say the flip.
הכא כיון דמינוול hacha kivan d'minaval in the case of the מת
meis to put them in such a compressed way לא מיקרי קבר.
lo mikrei kever.
So that's like you know that is I don't care what your
emergency was, okay, it's you know there's a fundamental sense that it's
like improper, not respectful, and therefore it does not like establish this
place as a graveyard because you basically say the bodies are not
being treated properly, you know, so it loses sort of that so
whatever the reasons were, it's not sort of they're not being presented
and being treated in the right way and therefore it doesn't have
that status.
התם מימר אמר האי מנייהו דשפיר שפיר דלא שפיר ליהוי לציבי. hatam
meimar amar hai minaihu d'shapir shapir d'la shapir l'hevei l'tzivei. But I
can very much understand that somebody planted an extra vine but didn't
want it to sort of continue you know wasn't planning on it
remaining there and operating as part of the vineyard. He said I'm
going to plant four and I'll see which ones are you know
are good and you know and the one that is not doing
so well I'll just use it for firewood. Okay so therefore I
was always intending to respond to the argument the You don't plant
a vine with the intention of uprooting it. The answer is: Yes,
you do. You could plant four vines and you'll keep the best
three and you'll uproot the fourth. So we can pretend that the
fourth one is not there. Okay, whereas the הגר"א, ha-Gra, it's not
like he's denying that sometimes it might happen, but what he, you
know, and it wasn't like intended to stay there, but what he's
saying is when it does happen, it changes the nature of the
space. You can't consider that space a בית הקברות beis hakevaros when
they're being treated that way. Yes. Like standard practice when you're creating—
Is it? Yeah, like I've never planted trees, but I've planted, like,
garden— you always put way more than you're planning on usually cultivating
and then you thin it out.
Oh, interesting. There you go. So it makes a lot of sense.
Okay, although there's a difference in the minds between thinning and uprooting,
like, cause there're different, whatever, years or status of the plants. Aha.
Yeah, that's an interesting question. Like, the רשב"ם, Rashbam, by the way,
also says— he says not like I'm saying. He's not saying like
oh it was an emergency with the מת, meis, but nevertheless, it—
you can't consider it a graveyard because it's not respectful. He actually
says like the ironic thing, like since it's not respectful, you would
not have done it by an emergency, because even if it was
ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, you wouldn't have placed it there like as
an emergency thing because it's not respectful. So it must be the
only reason you're placing it there is because you don't know how
to make a graveyard, and it was all very intentional and you're
just an idiot and therefore it's not a graveyard because it wasn't
with the intention to move it, it was with a misunderstanding of
the appropriate treatment and therefore that's its status, you know, it doesn't
get that status, that was all very intentional. Okay, הדרן עלך המוכר
את הפירות. hadran lach hamocher es hapiros.
Maybe we have three more minutes, let's just— I think we can
read the next משנה. mishna. Okay,
האומר לחבירו, ha'omer lachavero, בית כור עפר אני מוכר לך. beis kor
afar ani mocher lach. Back to— it's so funny, it keeps on
shifting back and forth between like these questions of what's included in
this word and I don't know, things that are, I think, you
know, bigger topics. So anyway, המוכר בית כור עפר אני מוכר לך.
hamocher beis kor afar ani mocher lach. I am selling you a
בית כור— beis kor a space that's called a בית כור. beis
kor. כור kor is like a volume measure that you would use
for seed, but it's also a measure that translates into a, like,
an area measure, like an acre. Okay, and might be because the
רשב"ם Rashbam says it's not that way, but it might be because
it's seen like that's the amount of space you need to plant
this amount of seed. A seed, you know, the seed that fills
a כור, kor, you might need this amount of ground. So it's
called a בית כור. beis kor. Now, the basic point is, is
that 50 by 50 is called a בית סאה. beis se'ah. 50
by 50 אמות. amos.
Okay, and there are six בית קבים beis kavs
in a— one בית סאה, beis se'ah, because there are six קבים
kavs in a סאה. se'ah. A כור kor is— a בית כור
beis kor is 30 בית סאות. beis se'ahs. So that's pretty darn
large because this is like 75 by 75 feet. What would that
be? 75 by 75 feet, roughly.
What is that? 5,000 square feet about? 70 by 70 is 4,900...
it's about 5,000 square feet.
Okay. So that's 30 times that. So that's 150,000 square feet. That's
got to be pretty big, right? Whatever that is, you can do
the math. Okay. Anyway, so that's a בית כור. beis kor. So
someone says I am selling you a בית כור, beis kor, okay?
היו שם נקעים עמוקים עשרה טפחים, hayu sham neka'im amukim asarah tefachim,
או סלעים גבוהים עשרה טפחים. o sla'im gevohim asarah tefachim. So in
this big plot of land, there's like a big boulder, okay? That's
עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim high. And the רשב"ם Rashbam says ארבע אמות
arba amos wide by ארבע אמות arba amos wide, which is sort
of like the space of like a domain, right? ארבע אמות arba
amos by ארבע אמות arba amos by עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim high
and so on. Okay, and so it's this big— it's almost like
its own space. It's interesting that it does not say here the
width and the length but only says the height. Or it's עשרה
טפחים asarah tefachim deep, and again, the רשב"ם Rashbam says ארבע אמות
arba amos wide. אין נמדדין עמה. ein nimdadin imah. So then we
don't say I've got this, you know, big area, the בית כור,
beis kor, and right here there's like a big boulder, okay? So
do I include that in the area or do I say no,
that doesn't count, I gotta give you more space, you know, to
make up for that boulder because that boulder wasn't part of it?
So if it's its own space defined by עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim
high or עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim deep, and according to the רשב"ם
Rashbam ארבע אמות arba amos by ארבע אמות, arba amos, if it's
its own space, then it's a boulder in the middle of my
בית סאה beis se'ah but it's not part of the בית סאה.
beis se'ah. So you actually have to give, you know, more space
elsewhere to make up for that. פחות מכאן, pachas mikan, if it's
less than that height or depth,
נמדדין עמה. nimdadin imah. ואם אמר לו כבית כור עפר אני מוכר
לך, ve'im amar lo kibis kor afar ani mocher lach, כבית כור
עפר, kibis kor afar, like a בית כור. beis kor. So what
do I mean 'like'? How much? So that means— that means that
the whole land measures a בית כור beis kor but it's regardless
of these boulders and whatever. אפילו היו שם נקעים עמוקים יותר מעשרה
טפחים, afillu hayu sham neka'im amukim yoser me'asarah tefachim, או סלעים גבוהים
יותר מעשרה טפחים. o sla'im gevohim yoser me'asarah tefachim. הרי אלו נמדדין
עמה. harei elu nimdadin imah. עד דכא Ad dakei means that I
get to say like the lack of precision doesn't mean I can
give you nine-tenths of a בית כור; beis kor; lack of precision
means I give you a whole בית כור beis kor and regardless
of whether there are these like boulders or crevices and so on
that all gets counted in the area. Okay, so that's the משנה
mishnah to be continued tomorrow.